<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-rtcweb-transports-09"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="WebRTC Transports">Transports for WebRTC</title>

    <author fullname="Harald Alvestrand" initials="H. T." surname="Alvestrand">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <email>harald@alvestrand.no</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="18" month="March" year="2015"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the data transport protocols used by WebRTC,
      including the protocols used for interaction with intermediate boxes
      such as firewalls, relays and NAT boxes.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>WebRTC is a protocol suite aimed at real time multimedia exchange
      between browsers, and between browsers and other entities.</t>

      <t>WebRTC is described in the WebRTC overview document, <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview"/>, which also defines terminology used
      in this document.</t>

      <t>This document focuses on the data transport protocols that are used
      by conforming implementations, including the protocols used for
      interaction with intermediate boxes such as firewalls, relays and NAT
      boxes.</t>

      <t>This protocol suite intends to satisfy the security considerations
      described in the WebRTC security documents, <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch"/>.</t>

      <t>This document describes requirements that apply to all WebRTC
      devices. When there are requirements that apply only to WebRTC browsers,
      this is called out by using the word "browser".</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="app-transport"
             title="Transport and Middlebox specification">
      <t/>

      <section title="System-provided interfaces">
        <t>The protocol specifications used here assume that the following
        protocols are available to the implementations of the WebRTC
        protocols:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>UDP. This is the protocol assumed by most protocol elements
            described.</t>

            <t>TCP. This is used for HTTP/WebSockets, as well as for TURN/SSL
            and ICE-TCP.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>For both protocols, IPv4 and IPv6 support is assumed.</t>

        <t>For UDP, this specification assumes the ability to set the DSCP
        code point of the sockets opened on a per-packet basis, in order to
        achieve the prioritizations described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rtcweb-qos"/> (see <xref target="s-qos"/>) when
        multiple media types are multiplexed. It does not assume that the DSCP
        codepoints will be honored, and does assume that they may be zeroed or
        changed, since this is a local configuration issue.</t>

        <t>Platforms that do not give access to these interfaces will not be
        able to support a conforming WebRTC implementation.</t>

        <t>This specification does not assume that the implementation will
        have access to ICMP or raw IP.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Ability to use IPv4 and IPv6">
        <t>Web applications running in a WebRTC browser MUST be able to
        utilize both IPv4 and IPv6 where available - that is, when two peers
        have only IPv4 connectivity to each other, or they have only IPv6
        connectivity to each other, applications running in the WebRTC browser
        MUST be able to communicate.</t>

        <t>When TURN is used, and the TURN server has IPv4 or IPv6
        connectivity to the peer or its TURN server, candidates of the
        appropriate types MUST be supported. The "Happy Eyeballs"
        specification for ICE <xref
        target="I-D.martinsen-mmusic-ice-dualstack-fairness"/> SHOULD be
        supported.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Usage of temporary IPv6 addresses">
        <t>The IPv6 default address selection specification <xref
        target="RFC6724"/> specifies that temporary addresses <xref
        target="RFC4941"/> are to be preferred over permanent addresses. This
        is a change from the rules specified by <xref target="RFC3484"/>. For
        applications that select a single address, this is usually done by the
        IPV6_PREFER_SRC_TMP preference flag specified in <xref
        target="RFC5014"/>. However, this rule is not completely obvious in
        the ICE scope. This is therefore clarified as follows:</t>

        <t>When a client gathers all IPv6 addresses on a host, and both
        temporary addresses and permanent addresses of the same scope are
        present, the client SHOULD discard the permanent addresses before
        forming pairs. This is consistent with the default policy described in
        <xref target="RFC6724"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="s-middlebox" title="Middle box related functions">
        <t>The primary mechanism to deal with middle boxes is ICE, which is an
        appropriate way to deal with NAT boxes and firewalls that accept
        traffic from the inside, but only from the outside if it is in
        response to inside traffic (simple stateful firewalls).</t>

        <t>ICE <xref target="RFC5245"/> MUST be supported. The implementation
        MUST be a full ICE implementation, not ICE-Lite. A full ICE
        implementation allows interworking with both ICE and ICE-Lite
        implementations when they are deployed appropriately.</t>

        <t>In order to deal with situations where both parties are behind NATs
        of the type that perform endpoint-dependent mapping (as defined in
        <xref target="RFC5128"/> section 2.4), TURN <xref target="RFC5766"/>
        MUST be supported.</t>

        <t>WebRTC browsers MUST support configuration of STUN and TURN
        servers, both from browser configuration and from an application.</t>

        <t>In order to deal with firewalls that block all UDP traffic, the
        mode of TURN that uses TCP between the client and the server MUST be
        supported, and the mode of TURN that uses TLS over TCP between the
        client and the server MUST be supported. See <xref target="RFC5766"/>
        section 2.1 for details.</t>

        <t>In order to deal with situations where one party is on an IPv4
        network and the other party is on an IPv6 network, TURN extensions for
        IPv6 <xref target="RFC6156"/> MUST be supported.</t>

        <t>TURN TCP candidates, where the connection from the client's TURN
        server to the peer is a TCP connection, <xref target="RFC6062"/> MAY
        be supported.</t>

        <t>However, such candidates are not seen as providing any significant
        benefit, for the following reasons.</t>

        <t>First, use of TURN TCP candidates would only be relevant in cases
        which both peers are required to use TCP to establish a
        PeerConnection.</t>

        <t>Second, that use case is supported in a different way by both sides
        establishing UDP relay candidates using TURN over TCP to connect to
        their respective relay servers.</t>

        <t>Third, using TCP only between the endpoint and its relay may result
        in less issues with TCP in regards to real-time constraints, e.g. due
        to head of line blocking.</t>

        <t>ICE-TCP candidates <xref target="RFC6544"/> MUST be supported; this
        may allow applications to communicate to peers with public IP
        addresses across UDP-blocking firewalls without using a TURN
        server.</t>

        <t>If TCP connections are used, RTP framing according to <xref
        target="RFC4571"/> MUST be used, both for the RTP packets and for the
        DTLS packets used to carry data channels.</t>

        <t>The ALTERNATE-SERVER mechanism specified in <xref
        target="RFC5389"/> (STUN) section 11 (300 Try Alternate) MUST be
        supported.</t>

        <t>The WebRTC implementation MAY support accessing the Internet
        through an HTTP proxy. If it does so, it MUST support the "connect"
        header as specified in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-tunnel-protocol"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Transport protocols implemented">
        <t>For transport of media, secure RTP is used. The details of the
        profile of RTP used are described in "RTP Usage" <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-rtp-usage"/>. Key exchange MUST be done using
        DTLS-SRTP, as described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch"/>.</t>

        <t>For data transport over the WebRTC data channel <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>, WebRTC implementations MUST
        support SCTP over DTLS over ICE. This encapsulation is specified in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-sctp-dtls-encaps"/>. Negotiation of this
        transport in SDP is defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp"/>. The SCTP extension for NDATA,
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-sctp-ndata"/>, MUST be supported.</t>

        <t>The setup protocol for WebRTC data channels is described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-protocol"/>.</t>

        <t>Note: DTLS-SRTP as defined in <xref target="RFC5764"/> defines
        protection of data carried over a single UDP source and destination
        port pair (RFC 5764 section 3). In the context of using ICE, the term
        "single UDP source and destination port pair" needs to be understood
        as "a single ICE component", as defined in <xref target="RFC5245"/>.
        This note may be included in a future version of DTLS-SRTP or ICE.</t>

        <t>WebRTC implementations MUST support multiplexing of DTLS and RTP
        over the same port pair, as described in the DTLS_SRTP specification
        <xref target="RFC5764"/>, section 5.1.2. All application layer
        protocol payloads over this DTLS connection are SCTP packets.</t>

        <t>Protocol identification MUST be supplied as part of the DTLS
        handshake, as specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-alpn"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Media Prioritization">
      <t>The WebRTC prioritization model is that the application tells the
      WebRTC implementation about the priority of media and data flows through
      an API.</t>

      <t>The priority associated with a media or data flow is classified as
      "normal", "below normal", "high" or "very high". There are only four
      priority levels at the API.</t>

      <t>The priority settings affect two pieces of behavior: Packet markings
      and packet send sequence decisions. Each is described in its own section
      below.</t>

      <section anchor="s-qos"
               title="Usage of Quality of Service - DSCP and Multiplexing">
        <t>Implementations SHOULD attempt to set QoS on the packets sent,
        according to the guidelines in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rtcweb-qos"/>. It is appropriate to depart from
        this recommendation when running on platforms where QoS marking is not
        implemented.</t>

        <t>The implementation MAY turn off use of DSCP markings if it detects
        symptoms of unexpected behaviour like priority inversion or blocking
        of packets with certain DSCP markings. The detection of these
        conditions is implementation dependent. (Question: Does there need to
        be an API knob to turn off DSCP markings?)</t>

        <t>All packets arrying data from the SCTP association supporting the
        data channels MUST use a single DSCP code point.</t>

        <t>All packets on one TCP connection, no matter what it carries, MUST
        use a single DSCP code point.</t>

        <t>More advice on the use of DSCP code points with RTP is given in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-dart-dscp-rtp"/>.</t>

        <t>There exist a number of schemes for achieving quality of service
        that do not depend solely on DSCP code points. Some of these schemes
        depend on classifying the traffic into flows based on 5-tuple (source
        address, source port, protocol, destination address, destination port)
        or 6-tuple (5-tuple + DSCP code point). Under differing conditions, it
        may therefore make sense for a sending application to choose any of
        the configurations:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Each media stream carried on its own 5-tuple</t>

            <t>Media streams grouped by media type into 5-tuples (such as
            carrying all audio on one 5-tuple)</t>

            <t>All media sent over a single 5-tuple, with or without
            differentiation into 6-tuples based on DSCP code points</t>
          </list>In each of the configurations mentioned, data channels may be
        carried in its own 5-tuple, or multiplexed together with one of the
        media flows.</t>

        <t>More complex configurations, such as sending a high priority video
        stream on one 5-tuple and sending all other video streams multiplexed
        together over another 5-tuple, can also be envisioned. More
        information on mapping media flows to 5-tuples can be found in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-rtp-usage"/>.</t>

        <t>A sending implementation MUST be able to support the following
        configurations:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>multiplex all media and data on a single 5-tuple (fully
            bundled)</t>

            <t>send each media stream on its own 5-tuple and data on its own
            5-tuple (fully unbundled)</t>
          </list>It MAY choose to support other configurations, such as
        bundling each media type (audio, video or data) into its own 5-tuple
        (bundling by media type).</t>

        <t>Sending data over multiple 5-tuples is not supported.</t>

        <t>A receiving implementation MUST be able to receive media and data
        in all these configurations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Local prioritization">
        <t>When an WebRTC implementation has packets to send on multiple
        streams (with each media stream and each data channel considered as
        one "stream" for this purpose) that are congestion-controlled under
        the same congestion controller, the WebRTC implementation SHOULD cause
        data to be emitted in such a way that each stream at each level of
        priority is being given approximately twice the transmission capacity
        (measured in payload bytes) of the level below.</t>

        <t>Thus, when congestion occurs, a "very high" priority flow will have
        the ability to send 8 times as much data as a "below normal" flow if
        both have data to send. This prioritization is independent of the
        media type. The details of which packet to send first are
        implementation defined.</t>

        <t>For example: If there is a very high priority audio flow sending
        100 byte packets, and a normal priority video flow sending 1000 byte
        packets, and outgoing capacity exists for sending &gt;5000 payload
        bytes, it would be appropriate to send 4000 bytes (40 packets) of
        audio and 1000 bytes (one packet) of video as the result of a single
        pass of sending decisions.</t>

        <t>Conversely, if the audio flow is marked normal priority and the
        video flow is marked very high priority, the scheduler may decide to
        send 2 video packets (2000 bytes) and 5 audio packets (500 bytes) when
        outgoing capacity exists for sending &gt; 2500 payload bytes.</t>

        <t>If there are two very high priority audio flows, each will be able
        to send 4000 bytes in the same period where a normal priority video
        flow is able to send 1000 bytes.</t>

        <t>Two example implementation strategies are:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>When the available bandwidth is known from the congestion
            control algorithm, configure each codec and each data channel with
            a target send rate that is appropriate to its share of the
            available bandwidth.</t>

            <t>When congestion control indicates that a specified number of
            packets can be sent, send packets that are available to send using
            a weighted round robin scheme across the connections.</t>
          </list>Any combination of these, or other schemes that have the same
        effect, is valid, as long as the distribution of transmission capacity
        is approximately correct.</t>

        <t>For media, it is usually inappropriate to use deep queues for
        sending; it is more useful to, for instance, skip intermediate frames
        that have no dependencies on them in order to achieve a lower bitrate.
        For reliable data, queues are useful.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations are enumerated in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document is based on earlier versions embedded in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview"/>, which were the results of
      contributions from many RTCWEB WG members.</t>

      <t>Special thanks for reviews of earlier versions of this draft go to
      Eduardo Gueiros, Magnus Westerlund, Markus Isomaki and Dan Wing; the
      contributions from Andrew Hutton also deserve special mention.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4571'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4941'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5245'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5389'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5764'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5766'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6062'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6156'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6544'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6724'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-httpbis-tunnel-protocol'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-rtp-usage'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rtcweb-qos'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-sctp-dtls-encaps'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-sctp-ndata'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.martinsen-mmusic-ice-dualstack-fairness'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-alpn'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5128'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5014'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3484'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-protocol'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dart-dscp-rtp'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Change log">
      <t>This section should be removed before publication as an RFC.</t>

      <section title="Changes from -00 to -01">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Clarified DSCP requirements, with reference to -qos-</t>

            <t>Clarified "symmetric NAT" -&gt; "NATs which perform
            endpoint-dependent mapping"</t>

            <t>Made support of TURN over TCP mandatory</t>

            <t>Made support of TURN over TLS a MAY, and added open
            question</t>

            <t>Added an informative reference to -firewalls-</t>

            <t>Called out that we don't make requirements on HTTP proxy
            interaction (yet</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -01 to -02">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Required support for 300 Alternate Server from STUN.</t>

            <t>Separated the ICE-TCP candidate requirement from the TURN-TCP
            requirement.</t>

            <t>Added new sections on using QoS functions, and on multiplexing
            considerations.</t>

            <t>Removed all mention of RTP profiles. Those are the business of
            the RTP usage draft, not this one.</t>

            <t>Required support for TURN IPv6 extensions.</t>

            <t>Removed reference to the TURN URI scheme, as it was
            unnecessary.</t>

            <t>Made an explicit statement that multiplexing (or not) is an
            application matter.</t>
          </list>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -02 to -03">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Added required support for draft-ietf-tsvwg-sctp-ndata</t>

            <t>Removed discussion of multiplexing, since this is present in
            rtp-usage.</t>

            <t>Added RFC 4571 reference for framing RTP packets over TCP.</t>

            <t>Downgraded TURN TCP candidates from SHOULD to MAY, and added
            more language discussing TCP usage.</t>

            <t>Added language on IPv6 temporary addresses.</t>

            <t>Added language describing multiplexing choices.</t>

            <t>Added a separate section detailing what it means when we say
            that an WebRTC implementation MUST support both IPv4 and IPv6.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -03 to -04">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Added a section on prioritization, moved the DSCP section into
            it, and added a section on local prioritization, giving a specific
            algorithm for interpreting "priority" in local prioritization.</t>

            <t>ICE-TCP candidates was changed from MAY to MUST, in recognition
            of the sense of the room at the London IETF.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -04 to -05">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Reworded introduction</t>

            <t>Removed all references to "WebRTC". It now uses only the term
            RTCWEB.</t>

            <t>Addressed a number of clarity / language comments</t>

            <t>Rewrote the prioritization to cover data channels and to
            describe multiple ways of prioritizing flows</t>

            <t>Made explicit reference to "MUST do DTLS-SRTP", and referred to
            security-arch for details</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -05 to -06">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Changed all references to "RTCWEB" to "WebRTC", except one
            reference to the working group</t>

            <t>Added reference to the httpbis "connect" protocol (being
            adopted by HTTPBIS)</t>

            <t>Added reference to the ALPN header (being adopted by
            RTCWEB)</t>

            <t>Added reference to the DART RTP document</t>

            <t>Said explicitly that SCTP for data channels has a single DSCP
            codepoint</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -06 to -07">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Updated references</t>

            <t>Removed reference to
            draft-hutton-rtcweb-nat-firewall-considerations</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -07 to -08">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Updated references</t>

            <t>Deleted "bundle each media type (audio, video or data) into its
            own 5-tuple (bundling by media type)" from MUST support
            configuration, since JSEP does not have a means to negotiate this
            configuration</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
